MOHAMMAD ABDUL JABBAR



417/A 1st floor, Goran Adarsha school



munna_jabbar@yahoo.com



+88017-17501213



https://www.linkedin.com/in/abdul-jabbar

EDUCATION

Master in Environmental Sciences and Management
Jahangirnagar University
3.27 Out Of 4.00

Master of Science **(MSc.),** in Chemistry 2009–2010 Govt. Titumir College (National University) 2nd Class

Bachelor of Science **(BSc.)**, Major in Chemistry 2005-2006 Govt. Titumir College (National University) 2nd Class

CAREER HIGHLIGHTS

Experienced with a demonstrated history of working and strong professionalism in the various kind of manufacturing industries. Skilled in Chemical management, Environment protection, Root cause analysis, Negotiation, Analytical Skills, and Leadership. Ensuring safe and sustainable working environment and legal benefits of employees of the production facilities. Received several professional related training and Master's degree focused on Environment Sciences and Management from Jahangirnagar University.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

r-pac Bangladesh Limited (AEPZ)

Sr. Executive (Compliance & EHS)

24th June 2018 - Continuing

Responsible for developing Occupational Health & Safety Management System through National and International regulations, ZDHC guideline, HIGG Index, HIRA and Customers Code Of Conduct. Increase Awareness in production facility, developing Training materials based on audit findings and Customers COC. Guide the factory management to work on their improvement areas like ETP, Wastage Management, Use of Natural resources etc.

Assigned special task:

- Renew Legal License and Certification.
- Negotiation with Welfare Association, labor court and BEPZA Authority.
- Internal Audit.
- Accident Investigation.
- Follow-up on ISO & Other Certification.

Observing the production facilities practices especially Chemical Using process and taking into account of the environmental impact that arises from the production processes & steps. And also give guidelines to minimize the environmental threats.

RFL Group (Danga Industrial Park)

Asst. Manager (Compliance & EHS)

26th April 2017 - 27th March 2018

Supervised overall social compliance in response to health and safety and workers' benefits status of 12 manufacturing units. Responsible for developing a safe workplace by the help of National and International regulations, CDC requirements, IFC guideline, HIRA and Customers Code Of Conduct. Increase Awareness in production facility, developing Training materials based on audit findings and Customers COC. Guide the factory management to work on their improvement areas like ETP, Wastage Management, Use of Natural resources etc.

Assigned special task:

- Guide HRM Department according to legal requirement.
- Internal Audit.
- Developing Chemical Management System.
- Negotiation with CDC Finance Team, ERM Safety Professionals, Legal and Local Authorities.
- Accident Investigation.

RFL Group (Habiganj Industrial Park)

Asst. Manager (Compliance & EHS)

26th July 2015 - 25th April 2017

Supervised overall social compliance in response to health and safety and workers' benefits status of 20 manufacturing units. Responsible for developing a safe workplace by the help of National and International regulations, DEG requirements, ADB guideline, HIRA and Customers Code of Conduct. Increase Awareness in production facility, developing Training materials based on audit findings and Customers COC. Guide the factory management to work on their improvement areas like ETP, Wastage Management, Use of Natural resources etc.

Assigned special task:

- Guide HRM Department according to legal requirement.
- Negotiation with DEG & ADB Finance Team, ERM Safety Professionals, Legal and Local Authorities.
- Developing Chemical Management System.
- Provide Training to team members regarding Chemical Safety.
- Accident Investigation.
- Follow-up on ISO & Other Certification.

RFL Group (Habiganj Industrial Park) Trainee Executive (Compliance) 2015

20th January 2014 - 25th July

Assist HR & Compliance team to preparing documents. Regular Floor visit and report preparing. Implement Corrective Action plans with the help of floor personals.

AWARENESS TRAINING CONDUCT (At Workplace)

- **Chemical Handling**
- **Chemical Storage**
- Why MSDS/SDS?
- **GHS** labeling
- **Detoxification & ZDHC**
- **RSL & MRSL**
- EHS in Workplace
- Cylinder Safety
- Welding Safety
- Basic Fire Safety Awareness
- First Aid Training
- **Duty Of Fire Marshals**
- Duty Of Rescue Team
- Duty of Emergency Response Team Work at Height
- **Duty of Urgency**

- Electrical Safety in DB/SDB •
- Lightning Hazard
- Lock out and Tag out
- Hands and Finger Injury
- **Accident Investigation**
- Machine Safety & Guarding •
- Why PPE?
- PPE Selection and Use
- Permit to Work (PTW)
- Crane Safety
- Forklift Safety
- Confined Space Entry
- Fall Protection
- **Dropped Object**

- Risk Assessment
- **Process Risk Management**
- Factory HR Management
- Orientation & Assembly Importance
- Team Work
- **Duty Of Supervisors**
- Canteen Management
- Food Safety and Heath Hygiene
- **HIV Awareness**
- Waste Identification and Disposal
- **Grievance & Disciplinary Action**
- Importance of Social Compliance
- Labor Act & Rules
- BSCI COC (New)
- SEDEX COC

PROFESSIONAL TRAINING

Resource Efficient Management of Chemicals

Organized by: TUV Rheinland

Duration: 2 Days (July 28 - 29, 2017)

Occupational Health and Safety Management

Organized by: Training Institute For Chemical Industries (TICI)

Duration: 14 Days (October 16–27, 2016)

HR, Admin & Compliance

Organized by: BGMI

Duration: 5 Month (November 27, 2015 - March 18, 2016)

Environmental Management System (ISO 14001:2004)

Organized by: ITS Bangladesh

Duration: 1 Days (August 20, 2015)

Occupational Health and Safety Assessment Series (OHSAS 18001:2007)

Organized by: ITS Bangladesh

Duration: 1 Days (August 19, 2015)

Lean HRM

Organised by: r-pac Bangladesh

Duration: 2 Day

Think 5S

Organised by: r-pac Bangladesh

Duration: 1 Day

TOT on Microsoft Office Application

Organized by: Pran-RFL Group

Duration: 2 Day

REFERENCE

1. Ansarullah Al Masud

Compliance Officer, Bangladesh

NEXT Plc, GB Tower, Uttara, Dhaka-1230, Bangladesh

Cell: +8801911227769

Tel: +8802 58953526

E-mail: ansar_masud@nextsl.co.in

2. Major Md Mubashshirul Ibad (Retd.)

Head of HR & Admin

Unique Group, Gulshan, Dhaka

Cell: +8801678015551

E-mail: ibad@uniquegroupbd.com

mubashshir6856@yahoo.com

MOHAMMAD ABDUL JABBAR